All right, today's דף *daf* is דף י' *daf yud*. So we
pick up דף י' *daf yud*, we pick up from the very
top of דף י' *daf yud*. For whatever reason, our camera isn't
working today. All right, so at least but we're broadcasting live audio.
Anyway, איתמר *itmar*, top of דף י' *daf yud*. So we went
to a whole discussion about whether the husband is believed to say
פתח פתוח Pesach Patuach. *petaḥ patuaḥ* as opposed to that there was
no דם בתולים *dam betulim*. And then the question is whether the
consequences—and one consequence is that—that because he said that she had had
sex in a context in which the assumption that she had had
sex is enough of a basis to assume she committed adultery, then
like a case of an אשת כהן *eshes kohen*, for example, then
she'd be forbidden to him. But that's not because of anything objective,
just because he has to be bound by his own words, שוויא
אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא *shavya anafshei ḥaticha de-issura*. And then we also discussed
the interesting point or stated that he would be believed to make
her lose her כתובה kesubah. *kesuva*, which is particularly surprising because it's
just his claim. So we're going to look at that right now
and look at that in the context of the very nature of
כתובה kesubah. *kesuva* itself. So this is, we're about to see a
very important גמרא Gemara *gemara*, not the only one but one of
the major ones that discusses where does כתובה kesubah. *kesuva* come from.
So let's take a look. איתמר *itmar*, it was taught. אמר רב
Amar Rav, נחמן אמר Amar, שמואל משום רבי Rebbi, שמעון בן אלעזר
*amar rav naḥman amar shmuel mishum rabbi shimon ben elazar*: חכמים Chachamim
תקנו להם לבנות ישראל מאתים ולאלמנה מנה maneh, *ḥachamim tiknu lahem livnos
yisrael masayim u-le-almanah maneh*. This is a rabbinic institution, כתובה kesubah *kesuva*.
The rabbis instituted that virgins would get a כתובה kesubah *kesuva* of
מאתים *masayim* זוז zuz. *zuz*. That would be the lump sum paid
in a case of divorce or death and an אלמנה almanah, *almanah*,
widow, meaning a second marriage or the woman was otherwise not a
virgin as we'll see in משניות *mishnayos* coming up, מנה maneh *maneh*,
100 זוז zuz. *zuz*. והם הם האמינוהו *ve-hem hem eminu'hu*, since this
is all a rabbinic thing, they chose to believe him שאם אמר
פתח פתוח מצאתי Pesach Patuach matzasi. נאמן ne'eman. *she-im amar petaḥ patuaḥ
matzasi ne'eman*. Since the whole thing is that it was all a
rabbinic institution, they decided that even though normally it's a guy's claim—oh,
somebody owes someone $100 and he says I paid
or something of that nature—like, since when are you just believed by
this objective, you know, on your say-so? But nevertheless, this is a
rabbinic institution, so they chose to believe him when he said that
she was not a virgin, and not only based on absence of
blood, but even by his experience of פתח פתוח Pesach Patuach. *petaḥ
patuaḥ*, and they chose to believe that and to say that she
does not get her כתובה kesubah *kesuva*. So then the גמרא Gemara.
*gemara* says, okay look, we're not debating your right to say that.
I mean, if you instituted the כתובה kesubah, *kesuva*, you could say
whatever you want, whether you believe him or not. But the question
is: what good is it going to do once you've given somebody
the ability to always get out of it? So
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, אם כן מה הועילו חכמים Chachamim בתקנתם
*im kein mah ho'ilu ḥachamim betakkanasam*? How did the rabbis do any
good with their תקנה *takkana* because it'll—the guy will always have the
opportunity to just get out of it? אמר רבא חזקה chazaka? אין
In, אדם טורח בסעודה ומפסידה *amar rava ḥazakah ein adam toriaḥ bise'udah
u-mafsidah*. No, because we can assume that is not going to happen
on a regular basis, and we can assume that this is only
going to happen, you know, in the cases where—are, you know, pretty
much limited to the cases when it's true. What's our reason to
assume that it's only going to happen, or almost only going to
happen, in cases when it actually is true? Because he would not
want to waste all of his effort, you know, making this whole
wedding party and so on, just in order to go ahead and
have to divorce her the next day. So he would not be
making this up, or just in order to lose all of his
effort, he would not be making this up, you know, if it
weren't true. Now תוספות Tosfos *tosfos* asks an important question. What do
you mean he would not want to lose his effort? Like, maybe
he gets the best of both worlds: he stays married to her
and he doesn't have to pay her the כתובה kesubah, *kesuva*, or
doesn't have to pay her the full כתובה kesubah. *kesuva*. Rather than
paying her 200, which a virgin gets, he would only pay 100.
Now, so what you have to know is that there's a debate
in the גמרא Gemara *gemara* later, which is: if a man says,
"I expected that she was a virgin and I found she wasn't,"
ignoring any concern about adultery, that does it mean that the whole
thing was a מקח טעות mekach taut *mekaḥ ta'os*? The whole thing
was, you know,
it
was all on false premises and I never would have married her
had I known she wasn't a virgin. And therefore she gets zero
כתובה kesubah *kesuva*, and she basically maybe doesn't even need a גט
get. *get*, but certainly she gets divorced without a כתובה kesubah. *kesuva*
because the whole thing was on false premises. Or does this just
mean: oh, so then we just have to adjust the amount, right?
The amount was 200 because we wrote 200 because we thought she
was a virgin; turned out she wasn't a virgin, so we adjust
the amount down to 100, right? How drastic is it mon... in
terms what when he says she wasn't a virgin, even putting aside
the concern of what do you call it, of adultery? So that's
a debate later on. So תוספות Tosfos *tosfos* says that makes a
difference—how much he's risking right now, מפסיד *mafsid* his כיסו *kiso* סעודה
*se'udah*, how much is he risking by saying she's not a virgin?
So look at this little תוספות Tosafos. *tosfos*. חזקה אין אדם טורח
בסעודה *ḥazakah ein adam toriaḥ bise'udah*. So תוספות Tosafot *tosfos* says תימה
*teima*, this is a wonder, תינח *tinaḥ* באשת כהן *be-eshes kohen* או
בפחות מבת ג' *o bifḥus mibas gimmel*. If it's a case that
he's a כהן *kohen* or she was married under three, the cases
where we said that by saying she's not a virgin means he
has to assume that she committed adultery and he won't be able
to continue living with her so. In that case דמיתסרא ליה, his
claim she's not a virgin means that she's forbidden to him. So
there we would say he's not going to make this up and
make her forbidden to him, you know, just to save himself the
money of the כתובה. kesubah. Okay, הילכך, hilkach, כיוון
דמפסדה, keivan d'mifsada, נאמן. He's losing his wife. So if he's losing
his wife by this claim, right, because it basically translates into a
claim of adultery, he would not make this up just in order,
you know, after having spent $20,000 on the wedding and gone through
all this effort, he would not have made this up to have
one night of sex and then
to be forbidden to her just not to have to pay the
full כתובה. kesubah Okay, so there we can assume he's telling the
truth.
ולמאן דאמר נמי לקמן, U'leman d'amar nami l'kaman, כנסה בחזקת בתולה ונמצאת
בעולה, knesah b'chezkas besulah v'nimtzas beulah, אין לה כתובה כלל, ein la
kesubah klal, ניחא. nicha. Then it also makes sense. דהשתא נמי מפסדה,
D'hashta nami mifsada, שהרי מקחו טעות הוא, sheharei mekach taut hu, because
then what it's basically saying is the whole thing was false premises
and again, as a result of saying she's not a virgin, what
you're basically saying is you're not married to her. Okay, so
then they get divorced. So maybe they don't even need a גט.
get So if the result is you're not allowed to have sex
or that you have to get divorced or that you're already divorced,
then we could say you would never say anything so drastic if
it weren't true. But תוספות Tosafot says, אבל למאן דאמר יש לה
כתובה מנה, Aval l'man d'amar yeish la kesubah maneh, but all you
do when it turns out she's not a virgin is adjust it
down to a hundred, לא מפסיד מידי. lo mafsid midei. He's not
losing anything. He stays married to her, they keep all the wedding
gifts, they had the nice party, and he just has to pay
less for the כתובה. kesuvah אלא שבאה להפסידה מכתובתה מנה, Ella sheba
l'hafsidah miksubasah maneh, אבל הוא לא מפסיד, aval hu lo mafsid, ואמאי
מהימן? v'amai meheiman? Why is he believed? ויש לומר דלא מהימן. v'yeish
lomar d'lo meheiman. Fine, he wouldn't be believed. So although the גמרא
Gemara makes a blanket claim he's believed, תוספות makes a very reasonable
point that that really is only in contexts where there's a drastic
implications to him saying that she's not a virgin. Either she's assumed
to have committed adultery and she's forbidden to him, or it's a
מקח טעות mekach taut, and therefore they're not even married, but if
the only result of his statement is that he wants to make
the כתובה kesuvah adjusted down from 200 to 100, there's no reason
to think he's telling the truth. Okay, so that's an important, you
know, qualification on the statement of the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so that's
the man's claim that she's not a virgin and their willingness to
believe him, but now what the גמרא Gemara has introduced is the
idea that the whole idea of כתובה kesuvah was a rabbinic institution.
So let's take a look at that.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תני, Tani, we taught in
a ברייתא, Beraisa, הוי קנס חכמים הוא לא תגבה אלא מן הזיבורית.
Havi knas chachamim hu lo tigbeh ella min haziboris.
Since the כתובה kesuvah is a rabbinic fine, she can only collect
from the זיבורית. ziboris. There are three sort of grades of land:
Grade A, Grade B, Grade C. עידית Idis is Grade A, בינונית
beinonis is Grade B, זיבורית ziboris is Grade C, right? The worst
type of land. And even though if you have a debt of
like $1,000, you know, you can collect land worth a thousand dollars,
but where would you like your land worth a thousand dollars? Would
you like one square foot in New York City or would you
like 10 acres, you know, somewhere in some wasteland? They're both worth
a thousand dollars, but I'd rather have the one square foot in
New York City than the 10 acres in some wasteland. Okay, so
that's the issue about what type of a land are you collecting
from. So here the ברייתא Beraisa says since the whole thing was
rabbinic and it's not a real debt, right? It's sort of just
a created obligation that the rabbis did. So therefore, she's not—it's not
like she lent money and therefore she's entitled to collect it. I
mean, it is a real debt, but you know what I'm saying?
It didn't result from some type of a fact that some prior
obligation to her or something like that. So therefore, she can only
collect from the lowest quality land, I mean, if he wants to
limit her to that. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer, meaning in any case?
Like any case
a woman comes to collect her כתובה, kesuvah he can always say,
fine, you can collect it, but you have to go to my
worst land. You can't go to my Grade A land, you
have to go to my Grade C land. Does it have to
do with this חזקה?
No, no, no. This is just a general reflection of the fact
that this whole thing is a rabbinic institution.
But why did you think it was a קנס חכמים? knas chachamim?
Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to ask the word קנס. knas.
One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel אומר, omer, now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
קנסא מאי קנסא? Knasa mai knasa? What do you mean a fine?
What did he do wrong that we're fining him? אלא אימא הואיל
ותקנת חכמים הוא לא תגבה אלא מן הזיבורית. Ella eima ho'il v'takanas
chachamim hu lo tigbeh ella min haziboris. Fine, it's a rabbinic institution.
But nevertheless, it's not like, you know, if it were biblical, it
would be more weighty. If she had let's say lent him money
and therefore he owed her money, it would be more weighty. But
the whole thing is rabbinic and therefore it's not going to be
as weighty. Now, of course, the other thing—and therefore we're going to—and
now the other thing to keep in mind here is also that
the rabbis are constantly doing a little bit of a balance, you
know, in terms of like social engineering. Like you on the one
hand, you want to protect her, on the other hand, you don't
want the protections to be so high and the demands on the
husband to be so high that people are going to hesitate before
getting married. So you have to like exactly find like the perfect
balance. Okay. So, ah, well, that's not protecting her so much, giving
her that land. Fine, but on the other hand, if we were
to say higher quality land, maybe more men would hesitate before getting
married, right? And I mean, right now you have a whole huge
שידוך shidduch crisis, right? You know, so anyway.
And mostly because of, you know, זיבורית ziboris versus עידית? idis? That's
what the men are...
Maybe.
Maybe. Why would I marry her if I might lose my prime
New York real estate? Okay. Anyway, so רבן שמעון... Rabban Shimon... so
that's the... So that's the position. She collects, when she collects, he
can push her to get from the lower quality land. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר, omer, כתובת אשה מן התורה.
Kesubas Isha min HaTorah. It's not rabbinic, it's biblical, and therefore presumably
she would collect grade B or grade A. ומי אמר רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל הכי? U'mi amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hachi? Did Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel really say that? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, כסף ישקול כמהר הבתולות,
Kesef yishkol k'mohar ha-betulos, that what
the verse says by the man who seduces a virgin, that he
shall pay weigh out the silver, ישקול, yishkol, according to the מהר
mohar that normally gets that is given to virgins. And what exactly
מהר mohar means biblically is an important question.
The פשט pshat of the תורה Torah of course is that מהר
mohar is something given before or in the act of contracting the
marriage, right? Like when שכם Shechem says הרבו עלי מאד מהר ומתן
ואתנה כאשר תאמרו אלי, Harbu alai me'od mohar u-mattan ve-ettenah ka'asher tomeru
elai, right? And דוד David gives a מהר mohar in order to
marry מיכל, Michal, בת שאול. Bas Shaul. The מהר mohar is a
hundred ערלות orlos of the פלשתים. Plishtim. So anyway, so the רמב"ן
Ramban says that it means like some type of a traditional gift
that was given from the groom to the bride's family. But the
biblical scholars think that the much, much more פשט pshat is that
it actually was the bridal price as opposed to something symbolic like
we give like a פרוטה perutah or a ring. They used to
give a serious amount of money, and it was given to the
father. The father would be the one marrying off a daughter. You
have nowhere in תנ"ך Tanakh that a woman marries herself off. And
therefore it was a serious bridal price given from the groom to
the bride's father. Okay, but this becomes the basis for the rabbinic
institution of a כתובה, kesuva because as we're going to see, the
standard מהר mohar of בתולות betulos was 200 זוז. zuz. It was
50 שקל, shekel, and a שקל shekel is four זוז. zuz It
was 200 זוז. zuz And so what happened is the rabbis took
the 200 זוז zuz that initially was given up front as the
מהר mohar and instituted as a payment that would come at the
end in a case of death and divorce, and basically turned it
into our current institution of כתובה. kesuva.
So it starts with it starts
right so it starts with a biblical reality of מהר mohar but
it transforms into a rabbinic reality of כתובה kesuvah going from the
beginning of the marriage to the end. Okay, so let's take a
look.
כסף ישקול כמהר הבתולות. Kesef yishkol k'mohar ha-betulos. So if a man
seduces a virgin, so now she's not a virgin anymore, so now
nobody else is going to, you know, and the realities of that
society won't want to marry her. If they marry her they won't
want to pay the מהר. mohar. So since he's making her lose
the מהר, mohar, he has to give the מהר mohar to the
father because now the father's out the מהר. mohar. Damaged goods, right?
That's the sort of approach the תורה Torah has to that. So
therefore שזה כמהר הבתולות ומהר הבתולות כסף. She-zeh k'mohar ha-betulos u-mohar ha-betulos
kesef. So first of all it says this. Now what's the this?
So this is referring in this context to the case of the
מאנס, me'anes, the man who rapes a woman in דברים, Devarim, where
it says there he pays, you know,
חמישים כסף, chamishim kesef, fifty, you know, units of silver. Now and
that's 200 זוז zuz. but it's only 200 זוז zuz, because we
interpret that the word כסף kesef there means a שקל. shekel. And
the idea of שקל shekel we get from this פסוק pasuk here
by by the seducer, by ישקול. yishkol. So that's what it means.
שזה כמהר הבתולות. She-zeh k'mohar ha-betulos. So this where it says the
fifty is like the מהר mohar or this is like the מהר
הבתולות mohar ha-betulos that is mentioned, excuse me, by by the person
who rapes, which is fifty. ומהר בתולות U-mohar betulos and over there
where it says fifty by the amount by the מהר mohar of
virgins, כזה ka-zeh is like this which is שקל. shekel. So anyway
by combining this with the case of rape we get 50 שקל
shekel and we get 200 זוז. zuz Now fine, that's all מהר
mohar in the תורה, Torah, which is paid up front. And therefore
if a girl was seduced or raped and the father isn't going
to get the מהר mohar from another man, this man has to
give the מהר. mohar. But this then becomes the 200 זוז, zuz
the basis of the rabbinic כתובה. kesuvah מכאן סמכו חכמים לכתובת אשה
מן התורה. Mikan samchu chachamim le-kesubas isha min ha-Torah. This is from
here the rabbis get had a basis for their for the idea
of a woman's כתובה. ketubah They have a biblical basis for it.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כתובת אשה
אינה מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer kesubas
isha einah mi-divrei Torah ella mi-divrei Sofrim. It's not biblical, it's only
rabbinic. Okay, so we've I'm going to get so I'm going to
get back to discuss that because it's funny because even the first
position didn't seem like it was saying it was biblical, seemed like
it was saying there's a biblical basis for it. But so we'll
get back to that in a minute. But רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel seems to say there's not even a biblical
basis. The whole thing is a pure rabbinic institution. So now right
so now we got a contradiction because before you said it was
biblical and here he's saying it's a purely rabbinic institution. So what's
the story? So the גמרא Gemara says איפוך, Ipoch, reverse it. Fine,
this ברייתא braisa that has him saying rabbinic and the חכמים saying
biblical, reverse it. And in this ברייתא braisa he'll be the one
that says it'll be biblical. So the גמרא Gemara says ומה חזית
דאפכת בתרייתא איפוך קמייתא? U'mah chazis d'apchas basraisa ipoch kammaisa?
Why did you reverse this ברייתא? braisa? Why not reverse the earlier
statement where he said that it was where he said it was
rabbinic? Of course the earlier statement there was not a well, okay,
fine. So why not reverse the earlier statement? Why do you reverse
this one? So the גמרא Gemara, says השמיע ליה רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל דאמר כתובה מן דאורייתא. Ha shamina leih Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
d'amar kesubah min d'Oraisa.
No, because we have another source that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says that it is biblical. דתנן, De-tenan, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר נותן לה ממעות קפוטקיא. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
nosen lah mi-me'os Kapotkia. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you give her from
קפוטקיא Kapotkia the coin. What does that mean? So there's a משנה
mishnah later on which basically says that if a man... gets married
in קפוטקיא Kapotkia and contracts his כתובה there and divorces his wife
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, or he gets married in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and divorces his wife in קפוטקיא, Kapotkia, according to which
currency does he have to pay? Does he have to pay like
fifty שקל shekel of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael שקל shekel or קפוטקיא
Kapotkia שקל? shekel? Now, you and I would say, what do you
mean? I mean, he has to pay that amount in just translated
into the local currency. But for whatever reason, the משנה mishna there
assumes that no, since they both have a type of a שקל
shekel currency and they're both roughly equivalent, like think about US dollars
and Canadian dollars. I'm serious, like you call it the same thing,
they're pretty close. Okay,
there was a time when US dollars was more than Canadian dollars
and now it has Canadian dollars ever been more? It's getting close
now. It's been really close in the last like decade or so.
But okay, let's assume that that was it. So it was always
very close, but one was more. So fine, so the logic would
be that you pay based on the place where you got married,
where you contracted the obligation. And that's what קפוטקיא, Kapotkia, the money
was always worth more than in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, the
שקל. shekel. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says
in a case where you got married in קפוטקיא Kapotkia and you
divorce in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you pay based on where you
contracted the obligation. You pay based on קפוטקיא Kapotkia money even though
it's more. But the חכמים say no, you pay based on always
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. You always pay the lesser amount. Okay, now
what's the logic to say you always pay in Canadian dollars, right?
Shouldn't it depend on where you got married? So the logic is,
well, if the whole thing is rabbinic, we're gonna go easy on
you and we're gonna say you always pay in Canadian dollars, not
in US dollars. Okay, but רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says no, if you contracted in the US, you pay
in
US dollars.
So that shows, the גמרא Gemara, says that reflects an idea similar
to the discussion before about grade C land or grade A land,
that reflects an idea that he treats it as a serious obligation
and not just as a rabbinic obligation.
Okay, so does it mean that it's דאורייתא? de-Oraisa? It just means
it's a stronger rabbinic.
I understand. So it's not, yeah, it's not conclusive. But the גמרא
Gemara sort of sees that. So the גמרא Gemara says it makes
sense that we combine the statements of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel to think that he is the one that says
it's דאורייתא de-Oraisa and to reverse this ברייתא braisa that we just
quoted where he says it's דרבנן. de-rabbanan. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'is eima, and
if you want I could tell you, כולה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
היא. kulei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hi. The whole ברייתא braisa that
it made it sound like he was saying it was rabbinic, we're
gonna reread it to all be רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel and to have him say it's biblical. How? וחסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני. ve-chisurei mechsara ve-hachi tanni. It's missing some words. Here is
how you have to read it. מכאן סמכו חכמים לכתובה שהיא מן
התורה. mikan samchu chachamim le-kesuvah she-hi min ha-Torah.
Based on the פסוק pasuk of מוהר mohar is the basis for
the כתובה as a biblical basis. כתובה שהיא מן התורה. kesuvah she-hi
min ha-Torah. Wait,
I lost my place. כתובת אלמנה kesuvas almana however, introducing a totally
new thing that wasn't in the ברייתא, braisa, כתובה for a widow,
אינה
מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים, eina mi-divrei Torah ela mi-divrei sofrim, because
you never have in the תורה Torah מהר הבתולות, mohar ha-besulos, you
never have a מוהר mohar for women that are not
בתולות. besulos. אינה מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים. eina mi-divrei Torah ela
mi-divrei sofrim. שרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כתובת אלמנה אינה מדברי תורה
אלא מדברי סופרים. she-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer kesuvas almana eina mi-divrei
Torah ela mi-divrei sofrim. So basically we reconcile it by having him
say when he said it was rabbinic, he didn't mean a virgin's
כתובה is rabbinic, he meant a non-virgin's כתובה is rabbinic. Okay, but
anyway so we've reconciled and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel now is the one that says that it is biblical. So
now I want to say something. Fine, but it is interesting that
even the position that it's biblical has the language of סמכו, samchu,
right? It's a biblical basis, not that it's direct biblical. And the
reason for that is exactly what I said, which is that yes,
the idea of two hundred זוז zuz for בתולות besulos is in
the תורה, Torah, but it's a different phenomenon. It's coming up front.
So the rabbis based on that or transformed the upfront payment to
a payment at the end. They converted it, as it were, they
transformed it. So it's not that it's the direct biblical obligation, it's
a rabbinic re-application of the biblical. So it's an interesting mix of
biblical and rabbinic even according to the approach of דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. That
helps answer a question that all the ראשונים Rishonim ask, which is
all the ראשונים Rishonim say, it seems from other גמרות Gemaras that
we פוסקין paskin that כתובה is דרבנן. de-rabbanan. However, in אשכנזי Ashkenazi
כתובות kesuvos what we write is, מוהר בתולייכי דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא. mohar
besulayichi de-chazi lichi mi-de-Oraisa. Right? I'm obligating myself the two hundred זוז
zuz, of your מוהר, mohar, we use the language of מוהר, mohar,
your virginal מוהר mohar that is fitting to you biblically. So the
ספרדים Sephardim don't say that. The ספרדים Sephardim just have it say
דחזי ליכי. de-chazi lichi. They don't have the word מדאורייתא. mi-de-Oraisa. But
they still say מוהר. mohar. But the אשכנזים Ashkenazim say דחזי ליכי
מדאורייתא. de-chazi lichi mi-de-Oraisa. So the question is how can we say
דאורייתא de-Oraisa if all of the סוגיות sugyas seem to indicate that
it's דרבנן. de-rabbanan. Okay, so if you take a look at the
first תוספות. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל חכמים תיקנו. Amar Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel chachamim tiknu. משמע דכתובה דרבנן. mashma de-kesuvah de-rabbanan. וכן באשה
רבה ve-chen ba-isha rabba גבי gabbei אין לה כתובה ein lah kesuvah
קאמר לה kamar lah מאי טעמא תיקנו לה רבנן כתובה mai ta'ama
tiknu lah rabbanan kesuvah שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה. she-lo te'hei kalla
be-einav le-hotzi'ah. אלמא alma סתמא דש"ס stama de-shas סברי savrei דכתובה דרבנן.
de-kesuvah de-rabbanan.
The assumption of the סתמא stama of the גמרא, Gemara not רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel but the סתמא stama of
the anonymous גמרא, Gemara is that it's דרבנן. de-rabbanan. וקשיא ve-kasha דנהגו
לכתוב בכתובות de-nahagu lichtov be-kesuvos מאתיי זוז masai zuz דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא.
de-chazi lichi mi-de-Oraisa. דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא, dechazi lichi midoraisa,
how we write מדאורייתא. midoraisa. So one answer of תוספות is he
manages to say, yeah, we do פוסק paskin it's דאורייתא. deoraisa. The
other classic answer that people like quoting is in the name of
הרא"ש, the Rosh, which is that the obligation is rabbinic, but the
way we figure out the amount and the way or the way
we figure out what type of money you pay and how sort
of like this whole case of קפוטקיא Kapotkia but even a more
complicated issue is based on biblical coinage. Okay, but the obligation is
rabbinic. I think the answer is obvious. I think the answer is
is it דרבנן derabbanan or is it דאורייתא? deoraisa? And the answer
is yes. It's דרבנן derabbanan and it's דאורייתא. deoraisa. So כתובה is
דרבנן derabbanan in the current form we have, but it's דחזי ליכי
מדאורייתא, dechazi lichi midoraisa, it ultimately originates in a biblical obligation of
200 זוז zuz, of the מוהר. mohar. So the exact point of
סמכו חכמים כתובת אישה מן התורה, samchu chachamim kesuvas isha min hatorah,
it originates in the תורה Torah but in the end it's a
rabbinic institution is the reality that we actually פוסק paskin that it's
both
דרבנן derabbanan and
דאורייתא. deoraisa. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
So that was a very important גמרא Gemara in terms of the
basic nature of כתובה. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרב נחמן. Hahu de-asa kamei
de-Rav Nachman.
A man came to רב נחמן Rav Nachman back to פתח פתוח.
petach patuach אמר ליה פתח פתוח מצאתי. Amar lei Pesach Patuach matzasi.
I when I had sex with my wife and first time and
it seemed like she was already not a virgin based on just
the physical experience. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said אכספוהו כופרי. asvuhi kufrei. Go beat him
with these basically palm branches with thorns coming out of him. So
basically you’re going to go give him lashes with these
what is those things, is it a cat o' nine tails, things
that actually have the not just the lash but things that actually
have spikes on them? Barbed barbed lashes or something, right. So that's
what he did. Right now why? So the גמרא Gemara says what
so he says מב רחתא ליה, mavrachta chavita lei, it must be
that he was basically had prostitutes underneath him. So what does this
mean? So there's two interpretations of מב רחתא. mavrachta. How does he
know? How does he know what it feels like to have sex
with a virgin vs. a non-virgin? Must be that he's been fooling
around a lot. So let's beat this guy's been promiscuous and now
he's going ahead and complaining about his wife? So give him lashes
for his promiscuity. So one explanation is give him lashes for his
promiscuity. That's what רש"י Rashi does. תוספות says
the opposite. The only way he would know would be if he
was promiscuous. So therefore and we're not going to assume he was
promiscuous beforehand. So obviously he then he's lying. So give him lashes
for being מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra for libeling for slandering
his wife. So either way either he's slandering his wife or he's
been or he's been sleeping around and either way he should get
beaten
up for this.
So
that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. So the גמרא Gemara
says והא רב נחמן הוא דאמר מהימן. v'ha Rav Nachman hu d'amar
meheiman. But רב נחמן Rav Nachman says if a man says this
he's believed, right? So the גמרא Gemara says yeah, מהימן, meheiman, he's
believed, ומסקינן ליה כופרי, u-maskinei lei kufrei, and we beat him up.
So which then works with the idea. So fine, we're not saying
that he's libeling his wife, we're just saying that it's evidence that
he's been sleeping around, that he's been promiscuous. Just because he's been
promiscuous before doesn't mean that he's not believed. So he's believed that
his wife wasn't a virgin but we're going to give him lashes
because he's basically telling us that he's been sexually active. Okay, so
that's the compromise. So obviously if you have that type of a
position, not too many people are going to come and say that
they פתח פתוח מצאתי. Pesach Patuach matzasi.
אמר ליה מצאתי גם בתולים.
Amar
lei matzasi gam besulim.
That would be a different story.
Right. So that is true. He could still say that there was
no blood. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says and now the
גמרא Gemara says what David says. רב אחאי
משני כאן בבחור כאן בנשוי. Rav Achai mishani kan bevachur kan benasui.
No, it matters whether it was a first marriage or a second
marriage. If he had already been married then he'd be believed. If
he hadn't been married before then he's not believed. And now it
changes a lot of what we said before. That if he hadn't
been married before we don't believe him.
And he wouldn't be getting lashes?
Well no then he'd be getting lashes because he'd be he'd been
being מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra on his wife.
So even though he said so he was married before married once
then he marries this woman the second time and this other woman
the second marriage and he says פתח פתוח. petach patuach, He's believed.
And he wouldn't get... No no you only...
No but if he hadn't been married before he's not believed and
he gets lashes. Okay. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל. Hahu de-asa kamei
de-Rabban Gamliel. A person came to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. אמר ליה
Amar lei said to him פתח פתוח מצאתי. petach patuach matzati, Again
I found an open door. My wife wasn't a virgin but again
not because of basis of the blood just because of what I
the experience of the sex. אמר ליה Amar lei he said to
him שמא הטיתה. shema hititasah.
Maybe you sort of inclined maybe the way you actually had the
intercourse was one in which you didn't feel the rupture of the
hymen because you sort of like we'll see how the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara*, the למשל *lemashal* the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gives. Okay, but you
came in at an angle basically. אמשול לך משל *Emshol lecha mashal*,
let me give you a משל *mashal*, a parable. למה הדבר דומה
לאדם שהיה מהלך באישון לילה ואפילה *Lemah hadavar domeh leadam shehayah mehalech
bishon laylah va'afelah*. A person was going in the dead of night
and in darkness. Okay, because this apparently if you're basically if you've
never had sex before, you're you know you're sort of going in
the dark. You don't know what you're doing. Okay,
maybe sex is done in the dark also because maybe you know
just if you sort of take a look as you know for
sort of comparing the door and the man, so whatever. Okay, I
won't be too graphic, but you can figure it out in terms
of what the alleyway that's going down in order to get to
the door sort of might also be the point here.
Thanks for that, I know. So שהיה באישון לילה ואפילה *shehayah bishon
laylah va'afelah*, הטה *hita*, so הטה *hita* if he leaned against his
door and he came to the door of his house. If he
leaned against it, מצא פתוח *matza patuach*, you'll think it was it
was open. But really what he did was he just accidentally went
in through a crack or something on the side. Right? But he
didn't realize that the door had really been closed. His experience was
that it was open because he came in at an angle and
he went through a crack. It seems to be the point. Okay,
לא הטה *lo hita*, but if he had not sort of gone
in at an angle, מצא נעול *matza na'ul*, then he would realize
that the door had been closed. He'd come in at a perpendicular
and he would realize that it was closed. But because he didn't
know what he was doing and he came in at an angle,
it seemed to him that it was open. All right, so that's
the משל *mashal*. Basically, you didn't know what you were doing. Okay,
so
which is basically the point before the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. A person
could say פתח פתוח petach patuach *petach patuach* because he doesn't really
know. But I guess before maybe you don't know what it feels
like here, sort of like because you came in an angle you
didn't- anyway, whatever. But you didn't know what you were doing and
that's why it showed up that way. Okay. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri,
*Ika d'amri*, some say הכי אמר ליה amar lei. *hach'i amar leih*,
this is what he said to him: שמא במזיד הטיתו ועקרת לדשא
ולאברא *Shema bemazid hitatso va'akarta ledasha ve'avara*.
Maybe you did it intentionally. But intentionally probably means more like forcefully.
Okay. And therefore you ripped out the door and the bolt. So
meaning you came in so strong that you didn't feel the obstruction
of the hymen. Okay. אמשול לך משל *Emshol lecha mashal*, let me
give you an example. למה הדבר דומה לאדם שהוא מהלך באישון לילה
ואפילה *Lemah hadavar domeh leadam shehu mehalech bishon laylah va'afelah*. A man
going in dark, הטה במזיד *hita bemazid*, if he you know pushes
his door in like forcefully, so מצא פתוח *matza patuach*, it looks
like the door's open. I don't really get that because you know
a door's a door, you feel it, but maybe it didn't feel
like it was locked. Meaning the question is was it open or
was it closed, but was it locked or was it unlocked? So
if you basically just barrel through the door, you won't realize that
you broke through the lock
and that it had been locked. Okay. לא הטה במזיד *lo hita
bemazid*, if you didn't sort of come barreling through the door, מצא
נעול *matza na'ul*, you'd realize it had been locked. So one way
or the other, if you don't know what you're doing, you can't
really make this claim. Okay. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל *Hahu de'ata
lekamei deRabban Gamliel*, a man came to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban
Gamliel* בר רבי Rebbi, *bar Rabbi*, the son of רבי Rabbi. *Rabbi*.
אמר ליה amar lei. *Amar leih*, said to him, רבי Rebbi. *Rabbi*,
בעלתי ולא מצאתי דם ba'alti velo matzati dam, *ba'alti velo matzati dam*.
Now we get to a claim that apparently is not contested, right?
The whole thing that was contested was פתח פתוח petach patuach *petach
patuach*. Maybe you don't know what you're talking about, what experience have
you had before? But here it's the type of thing that they
did. They had a sheet and they had people outside making sure
nobody was cheating and they went ahead and they looked and there
was no blood. So this would seem to be the one claim
that is believed.
Okay. So the son of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* then
was the older one? Presumably.
I'm not sure. That's a good point. I'm not sure. No, what
does it say?
It says
the great-grandson of the רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* mentioned in
the previous instance. Yes. Right. There's three רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban
Gamliel*s. There's רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel הזקן *Rabban Gamliel Hazaken*, which is
in times of בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*. There's רבן גמליאל
דיבנה *Rabban Gamliel deYavneh*, which was like a great-grandfather of רבי Rebbi,
*Rabbi* or something, and this is רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* the son
of רבי Rebbi, *Rabbi*, which was- so this is like the third
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*. But you're right, it's not the standard רבן
גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*. The standard רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* is the רבן
גמליאל דיבנה *Rabban Gamliel deYavneh*. Okay.
And it says ראש *Rosh* has the reading רבן גמליאל בר רבי
*Rabban Gamliel bar Rabbi* in the previous incident.
Oh, so had the previous one, okay, interesting. Okay. בעלתי ולא מצאתי
דם ba'alti velo matzati dam, *Ba'alti velo matzati dam*. Okay,
there was no blood, which is one he should definitely be believed
on. So now let's see finally what she said, right? She's been
silent all this time. So אמרה לו *amra lo*, so she said
to רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, רבי *Rabbi*, בתולה betula, הייתי *betulah hayiti*.
I was a virgin. Meaning I'm not anymore. What can I tell
you that he didn't find blood? But let me tell you I
was a virgin on my wedding night. אמר להם *Amar lahem*, he
said to them,
הביאו לי אותו סודר *havi'u li oto sudar*. Bring me the sheet.
Bring me you know the thing where you were supposed to find
the blood on. הביאו לו hevi'u lo. הסודר *Heviu lo hasudar*, they
brought it to him. I shouldn't say the blanket, I should say
the sheet, excuse me. Bring me the sheet. הביאו לו הסודר *Heviu
lo hasudar*. ושראו במים
*Veshar'o bemayim*, he immersed it in water. וכבסו *Vechibso*, and cleaned it.
ומצא עליו כמה טיפי דמים *Umatza alav kamma tipei damim*, and found
some drops of blood because you know they did not have the
most hygienic settings then, so their stuff was probably completely dirty you
know. So it says, of course you didn't see the blood, look
how dusty and dirty the sheet is. So he cleaned the shirt,
not enough to get off the blood, but enough to get off
the dirt, and there was the drops of blood. אמר לו Amar
lo, *Amar lo* set him לך זכי במקחך go,
you know, take possession of your purchase. Okay, so again, the whole
idea here, I mean, talk about, you know, the different ways in
which the woman is sort of the object in all of these
discussions, so before it was a door that you had to get
through, now she's something that the man purchased. Okay, but again, also
the idea of purchase, right, because he's paying 200 זוז, zuz. and
if she isn't a virgin, then he shouldn't have to pay the
200 זוז, zuz he should only have to pay the 100 זוז.
zuz, I mean, these are the types of assumptions that are being
worked on here, or maybe he doesn't pay anything, that was the
point before about מקח טעות, mekach taut, maybe the whole thing is
off. Okay, אמר ליה. amar lei,
Again, notice the phrase מקח טעות, mekach taut, right, מקחך. mikchacha. So
is it a מקח טעות, mekach ta'us right, is it a mistaken
purchase, or is it a good purchase? So it was a good
purchase. אמר ליה. amar lei, Okay, so now, הונא בריה דרבא מפרזיקא
לרב אשי. Huna brei d'Rava miParzika l'Rav Ashi. So Mar the son
of of Rava said to Rav Ashi, אנן נמי נעביד הכי, anan
nami na'avid hachi, when we have these issues that somebody says there's
no blood, why don't we also clean the garment, clean the the
sheet? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said, because גיהוץ שלנו ככיבוס שלהם,
gihutz shelanu k'chibus shelahem, because they for them, they have Rashi says
good water, you know, they have very whatever it is. So there
when they do a simple laundry, that's for us to get to
their stage the stage for them of doing a laundry, for us
we would have to do like a real type of like a
serious cleansing, okay, גיהוץ, gihutz, גיהוץ gihutz is like serious use of
soap and rubbing against a rock, and so so it's not we
can't just do this by putting it in water.
So the Gemara says ואי אמרת
נעביד
גיהוץ, v'i amrat na'avid gihutz, okay, let's do the גיהוץ gihutz in
order to get off the dirt? No, because once you clean it
that degree and you use all these cleansing agents, so in that
case מעבר ליה חומרא, ma'aver lei chumra, the חומרא chumra which Rashi
says the rock that you rub against in order to do the
גיהוץ, gihutz, that would also take off the blood. So we cannot
do something that gets rid of the dirt without getting rid of
the blood. Okay, ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל בר רבי. hahu d'ata
l'kamei d'Rabban Gamliel bar Rabbi.
Another person came to Rabban Gamliel bar Rabbi. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
said to him, רבי בעלתי ולא מצאתי דם. Rabbi ba'alti v'lo matzati
dam. I had sex with my wife on the wedding night and
there was no blood. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so the wife said,
רבי עדיין בתולה אני. Rabbi adayin betula ani. I'm still a בתולה,
betula, not I was a בתולה, betula, I'm still a בתולה, betula
right? He did not actually succeed in having intercourse, so now he's
blaming it on me. So אמר להן, amar lahen, so he said
to them, הביאו לי שתי שפחות. havi'u li shtei shfachot. Bring me
them he means like servants. Bring me two maidservants, אחת בתולה ואחת
בעולה. achat betula v'achat be'ula. One virgin and one a non-virgin. הביאו
לו. They brought them. והושיבן על פי חבית של יין. v'hoshivan al
pi chavit shel yayin. And he had them sit on top of
an open barrel of wine. Okay, בעולה ריחה נודף. be'ula reicha nodef.
The one who had had sex the you know her she a
smell came from her. בתולה אין ריחה נודף. betula ein reicha nodef.
The בתולה betulah did not. So basically the image here Rashi says
is that if she is a non-virgin, so then there's nothing there's
no obstruction, so the fumes that come from the wine barrel go
up her lower orifice and come up through her body and out
of her mouth, and therefore you can smell the wine through her
mouth, but the other one that doesn't happen for her. Okay, so
this is a way of testing whether or not she was a
virgin. אף זו הושיבה. af zu hoshiva. So now that we've we've
seen that this test works, okay, so now we've done an experiment
and we've actually done a trial run and we see that it
works, so therefore on people that we know, we know one woman
you know was a virgin and one wasn't, and look the test
worked. So now we're going to try it with this woman when
we don't know what her status was. אף זו הושיבה. af zu
hoshiva. So put her on the barrel of wine, this woman, ולא
היה ריחה נודף. v'lo haya reicha nodef. And her no smell came
out of her. So clearly she was a virgin. אמר לו לך
זכי במקחך. amar lo lech zchi bemikchacha. Oh, go take your purchase,
you know, you thought you had sex, you didn't really succeed in
penetrating, you didn't really succeed in intercourse, so go try again, but
your wife is still your wife is a virgin. So the Gemara
says וניבדוק מעיקרא. v'nibdok mei'ikara. Why didn't they have to first try
it with the maidservants? Why not just do the test right away
בגופה? begufa? By her? So no, גמרא הוה שמיע ליה. gemara hava
shmia lei. He had a tradition that that this test would work,
but מעשה לא הוה חזי. ma'aseh lo hava chazi. He never actually
tried out his tradition, right? He was testing it. The relevance like
you know actually conduct the experiment and not go on I understand.
So now you'd say, oh what do you mean, aren't we supposed
to go by מסורה? mesorah? So the Gemara says no, he didn't
question the מסורה. mesorah. What he questioned was his ability to know
that he would be able to do the test in the right
way, okay, because who knows what type of a barrel of wine,
how open it has to be, like who knows if you know
exactly how to do it just because you have it, you know
it like you know intellectually, or you know you've been taught you
know you've been told it. Doesn't mean you know how to do
it in practice. Okay, וסבר דילמא לא קים ליה בגווה דמילתא שפיר.
v'savar dilma lo kim lei begava demilta shapir. Maybe he doesn't really
know how to do the how to do the test well. So
he had to first check to show that he actually knew how
to do the test well, and then he was able to go
ahead and use it. Okay, ולאו אורח ארעא לזלזולי בבנות ישראל. v'lav
orach ar'a lezalzulei bivnot Yisrael. And he did not want to you
know sort of treat in a non-respectful way a Jewish woman to
make her go through this test if it wasn't going to prove
anything. Okay. So why don't they do that you know then now
so to speak? If that what could I tell you? Because we
don't know how to do it. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל הזקן.
hahu d'ata l'kamei d'Rabban Gamliel haZaken. A person came to the elder
Rabban Gamliel, okay, which is the Rabban Gamliel time of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל הזקן. Hahu de'ata lakamei
deRabban Gamliel Hazaken. Now, a person came to the elder רבן גמליאל,
okay, which is the רבן גמליאל at the time of the בית
המקדש.
אמר לו, Amar lo, and
he said to him, רבי, בעלתי ולא מצאתי דם, there's no blood.
אמר לו, so the wife said, רבי, ממשפחת דורקני אני, mimishpachat Durkani
ani, I am from the family of דורקני Durkani שאין להם לא
דם נדה ולא דם בתולים she'ein lahem lo dam niddah velo dam
besulim that they do not have, they don't have דם נדה dam
niddah and they don't have, what do you call it, hymenal blood.
Okay, now I have no idea about, if Charlie was here, he
could tell us right away, yeah, how do they get pregnant if
they don't have menstrual bleeding?
I assume it's possible that there's a condition in which the, in
which, you know, people don't have
a hymen or have very thin hymen or something, that there's no
hymenal blood. I'm sure if Charlie was here, he would have told
us already. Okay, but anyway, but I don't know this thing about
not having any menstrual blood. Anyway, but I am from a certain
type of a family that this, that we don't have this. They
didn't have this conversation with each other. Yeah, that's also a good
point, right? They went straight to the רבי. That's what happens if
you have the בית דין Beis Din ready the next morning. שאין
להם לא דם נדה ולא דם בתולים. she'ein lahem lo dam niddah
velo dam besulim. בדק רבן גמליאל בקרובותיה, Badak Rabban Gamliel bikrovoseha, and
רבן גמליאל investigated her relatives. I hope it wasn't meaning a sort
of a, an oral investigation. He had some conversations with her relatives.
Okay. ומצא כדבריה, Umatza kidvareha, and he found lo and behold what
she said was correct, that that actually was the reality. אמר, so
therefore, אמר לו לך זכה במקחך. Amar lo leich zachei bemikachacha. Go
and, you know, take possession of your purchase. Okay, again, this very,
you know, purchase and objectifying thing, which is pretty much runs through
this. אשריך שזכית למשפחת דורקני. Ashrecha shezachisa lemishpachat Durkani. Praised are you
that you merited the family of דורקני. Durkani. Now, why is this
a praiseworthy thing? I mean, don't they have the whole business of
נדה? Niddah? So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
So first now the גמרא Gemara interjects, okay, מאי דורקני? Mai Durkani?
So what does this דורקני Durkani mean? דור קטוע, Dor katu'a, a
cutoff generation. Because now the גמרא Gemara is going to deal with
the problem of how it should affect fertility. אמר רב חנינא, Amar
Rav Chanina, so therefore, רב חנינא Rav Chanina said, תנחומין של הבל
ניחמו רבן גמליאל. Tanchumin shel hevel nichamo Rabban Gamliel. רבן גמליאל gave
him, you know, meaningless consolation לאותו האיש, le'oso ha'ish, to that man.
I mean, it's true that she was a virgin, but it's not
like, oh, praised are you that
you got a woman from this family. It's actually a bad thing.
Why? דתני רב חייא, Detani Rav Chiya, כשם שהשאור יפה לעיסה, keshem
shehas'or yafeh la'isisa, the same way yeast is good for the dough,
so כך דמים יפים לאשה. kach damim yafim l'ishah. So blood is
good for a woman. Menstrual blood means that a woman is fertile.
You know, yeast sort of ferments and it causes, you know, things
to happen, it causes the dough to rise, right? And the woman
gets pregnant and her stomach rises, you know, sort of like rising
dough, you know, and yeast sort of has this like, you know,
like this, you know, smell, all type of a thing to it.
You know, so it seems to be that whole like comparison going
on. והרי זה כנודות. Ve'harei zeh kenodos. והריחו, Veheiricho, right? Anyway, so
okay, so we've got now woman as an object of purchase and
as a house with a door and with a, and now as
a dough that's rising because of the yeast of the blood. Baby
in the oven. Right, exactly, right, he's got one in the oven,
exactly. Okay. So ותנא משום רבי מאיר, Vetana mishum Rebbi Meir, כל
אשה שדמיה מרובים, kol ishah shedameha merubim, any woman who has a
lot of menstrual blood, בניה מרובים, baneha merubim, she will have a
lot of children, she is very fertile. So that I don't know
if that's if there's any correspondence to that. My guess is that
there isn't. But nevertheless, if there's no menstrual bleeding, how is a
woman supposed to get pregnant if there's no, you know, if there's
no uterine lining? So, and clearly they did, I mean because, you
know, קרובותיה, krovoseha, her mother or whatever it is, I mean. That's
a good point. That's a good point. Unless it never would have
perpetuated themselves. No, because it could have gone through the men, right?
Right, it could have, it could have gone through the men. It
says it's just point difficult for her but eventually she does conceive.
In order to answer Michael's question of how did they have relatives.
No, just that, yeah, that she is able to conceive. What I
understand why, what why is the footnote saying that or what's, what's
it answering, what problem is it answering? Oh, somebody married a דורקני,
Durkani, the marriage should not be annulled on. Oh, why don't you
just say that it's sort of like a מקח טעות because, oh,
okay, yeah, that's a good question too. If she was really infertile,
then you have to get into the whole אילונית ailonis type of
a question. Okay. Okay, so where are we? איכא דאמרי, כל אשה
שדמיה מרובים. kol ishah shedameha merubim. אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Amar
Rebbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, זכה במקחך אמר ליה, zachei bemikachacha amar lei,
do take, you know, good possession, you know, merit in your possession,
which is that it's a good thing. רבי יוסף ורבי אבין אמרי,
Rebbi Yosef veRebbi Avin amrei, נתחייב במקחך אמר ליה. nis-chayeiv bemikachacha amar
lei. Ah, you're stuck with your sort of purchase. Okay, it's not
that you merited your purchase. Okay. So בשלמא למאן דאמר נתחייב, Bishlama
leman d'amar nis-chayeiv, היינו דרבי חנינא. hainu deRebbi Chanina. That's the point
that because it's assumed that now she won't be so fertile or
not fertile at all. אלא למאן דאמר זכה, Ella leman d'amar zachei,
but if it's like you've merited in this, מאי זכותא? mai zachusa?
What merit is it? Which is a way of also asking what
did רבן גמליאל when he says אשריך, ashrecha, unless he was completely
lying. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דלא אתי לידי ספק נדה,
delo asi lidei sefek niddah, that then there's never an issue of
נדה Niddah and a doubt full of נדה Niddah and all of
that if there's no menstrual blood. Okay. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי. Hahu
de'ata lakamei deRebbi. A woman came to, a man came to רבי.
אמר ליה, said to him, רבי, בעלתי ולא מצאתי דם, there's no
blood. אמר ליה, so the wife said, רבי, עדיין בתולה הייתי, adayin
besulah hayisi, I was still a virgin. But ושני בצורת הוי ushnei
batzorot havei and it was a, I'm sorry, no it should be
עדיין בתולה אני adayin betulah ani or something, well we'll see what
happened. ושני בצורת הוי, ushnei batzorot havei, now these were years of
famine. ראה רבי שפניהם שחורים ra Rabbi shepneihem shechorim and he saw
that their faces were blackened due to, you know, undernourishment. Okay. צוה
עליהם והכניסום למרחץ, tziva aleihem vehichnisum lemerchatz, so he went ahead and
he had them, he had them bathe, והאכילום והשקום vehe'echilum vehishkum and
fed and gave them, you know, something to drink, והכניסום לחדר vehichnisum
lacheder and then he had them go back into some, you know,
into a bedroom. ובעלו ומצאו דם, veba'alu umatzu dam, they had sex
in there and therefore they found blood. Okay. אמר לו לכו זכו
במקחך, amar lo lechu zachu bemikkachcha, go and merit in your possession.
קרא רבי עליהם, kara Rabbi aleihem, so Rabbi read on them the
following verse: צפד עורם על עצמם, tzapad oram al atzmam, their skin
is cleaves to their bones, יבש היה כעץ, yavesh haya ka'etz, it
was as dried as wood. So what I don't get is, does
it mean they had sex but because they were so undernourished the
hymen didn't bleed or the hymen broke but their blood didn't come
out, you know, or does it mean I mean I don't get
it or because they were undernourished they actually were not able to
successfully have like full penetration or something? Yeah, I don't know. But
is this coming to tell you that, like you know, is this
the undermining all these claims? Right, so thank you for saying that.
Right, after all this thing of פתח פתוח מצאתי, right, we end
the סוגיא sugya and he's believed to this and he's believed to
make her lose her 200 זוז zuz. and da da da da
da, in the end we find out how that might be in
theory but in practice we try to sort of, you know, dismiss
a lot of these claims, you know, you know, we try to
say, well sure you want to come to בית דין beis din
and say that, first we'll beat you up then say it. How
many customers are you going to get after that, right? How many
people are going to say it? And then you're, oh well maybe
this maybe that, etc. You don't know what you're talking about. You
said פתח פתוח but you don't know what you're talking about. So
you're absolutely correct, it would creates like it's very, sometimes סוגיות sugyos
do that, that they lay out this whole sort of theoretical, you
know, these whole positions in theory and then in the end with
all the stuff that contradicts it and that undermines it in practice.
So what we say in practice that the הלכה's halacha before apply,
but how the real question always is not what's on the books
but how a פוסק posek is going to act. But we say
today, yeah, we don't, we don't deal with these types of things
today. Yeah, I have a feeling that the this second aspect is
dealt with more compassionately. That he actually saw that they were the
blood aspect is dealt with more compassionately than the פתח פתוח, like
the rabbis trying to help this couple, yes, whereas previously they're beating
him up, you know, for the open, right. Right, yeah, I mean
here it feels like the rabbi's acting a little bit more like
of a pastoral counselor and being, right, being helpful as opposed to
being, right, that this couple was also more open to a conversation,
right, as opposed to, right, that it's sort of less adversarial the
whole thing, right? That's a good point. Right, cause actually you have
both husband and wife coming to the rabbi as well, that's a
very good point. Okay, so let's move on. Finally we get to,
as with many מסכתות, masechtos, you know, it sort of it buries
the lead, what they what they say in the newspaper business it
buries the lead, okay. בתולה כתובתה מאתים, betulah kesuvatah masayim, although this
is not like יבמות Yevamos where to get to some of the
basic, you know, foundational stuff we had to wait three פרקים, prakim,
here we only have to wait to the second משנה, mishnah, okay.
בתולה כתובתה מאתים, betulah kesuvatah masayim, a virgin the כתובה amount is
200 זוז, zuz. ואלמנה מנה ve'almanah manah and a widow or a
non-virgin as we will see is only 100 זוז. zuz So we've
already laid the principle about where that comes from in the תורה,
Torah, this idea of מהר mohar that was normally given.
בתולה betulah. now if a woman is a virgin regardless of
her prior marital status, she could be a widow who's a virgin,
אלמנה, almanah, or a גרושה gerushah or divorcée, or חלוצה chalutzah who
undergone חליצה, chalitzah, מן האירוסין min ha'eirusin if she at until this
point not only in fact been a virgin but but also only
had אירוסין, eirusin, never had נישואין, nisuin, right? You understand once a
woman has נישואין nisuin and goes to the חופה chuppah and starts
living with her husband we're assuming even if she claims she's a
virgin or whatever, we're just not going to make the distinction. If
he had נישואין nisuin we're treating her as a בעולה be'ulah as
a woman who's had sex. But if she was married without נישואין,
nisuin, she just had אירוסין, eirusin, then we are going to treat
her still as a בתולה. betulah כתובתן מאתים kesuvatan masayim they still
get 200. So basically here's a trick question, who's how could you
have a woman who was married before and whose כתובה is 200?
And it's a case where she was not only did she not
have sex, that wouldn't suffice as an answer, but she only had
קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין, nisuin, okay. ויש להם טענת בתולים veyesh
lahem ta'anas betulim and in their cases because they're assumed to be
virgins, right? So that's the other point that's made here. She doesn't
have to claim she's a virgin. Any woman who basically remembers the
קידושין kiddushin and the נישואין nisuin were separated by let's say a
year at least if not more. So a woman had קידושין kiddushin
and then her husband gave her a גט three weeks later
before they ever had נישואין, nisuin, we'll just assume that
she's a virgin because קידושין kiddushin doesn't make us change our assumption.
Except in יהודה Yehuda where they had often have sex after קידושין.
kiddushin. Okay, but normally קידושין kiddushin does not make her make us
change our assumption so a woman could be an אלמנה, Almanah גרושה
gerushah etc., but if it was only קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין
nisuin we're assuming she's a virgin and she has 200 זוז. zuz.
But because we're assuming she's a virgin... virgin, if the next morning
the husband said, oh, the whole thing's a big mistake, you weren't
a virgin last night פתח פתוח or לא מצאתי דם lo matzati
dam etc. we can't say well, what did you expect she was
married before? No. He has a טענת בתולים. ta'anat betulim. He has
a claim against her that she wasn't a virgin. It's two sides
of the same coin. If she's getting two hundred זוז zuz. because
we're assuming she's a virgin, then he has a, then he has
a legitimate claim, you know, whatever the consequences of saying פתח פתוח
or לא מצאתי דם, lo matzati dam, that's a legitimate claim because,
because he, he had a right to assume she was a virgin.
That's the assumption that we're making. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara מאי אלמנה? Mai Almanah? So where does this
word אלמנה Almanah come from? So it's a fascinating question. It's a
biblical word but it's because the גמרא Gemara has an answer it
wants to give. So אמר רב חנא בגדתאה, Amar Rav Chana Bagdata'ah,
so said רב חנא Rav Chana from possibly Baghdad although we said
before that that was a seventh century city. אלמנה על שם מנה,
Almanah al shem maneh, because she gets a מנה, maneh she gets
only a hundred זוז. zuz So that's where the word אלמנה Almanah
comes from. So the גמרא Gemara said, אלמנה מן האירוסין מאי איכא
למימר? Almanah min ha'eirusin mai ika lemeimar? All right, we're going to
get to, we're going to get to that. So how about the
fact that a woman who's a widow from אירוסין eirusin gets two
hundred? So that doesn't fit the word מנה because מנה is a
hundred. So he says, no, איידי דהא קרי לה אלמנה, Aidi deha
kari lah Almanah, because a standard woman who's a widow, who's a
woman who is a widow from נישואין, nissuim, is called an אלמנה
Almanah because she only gets a hundred זוז. zuz. הך נמי קרי
לה אלמנה, Hach nami kari lah Almanah, so a woman who's a
widow even from אירוסין, eirusin, although she would get two hundred זוז
zuz for her next marriage, you know, we're talking about right, he
remarries her, next marriage she gets two hundred זוז. zuz Nevertheless, the
term אלמנה Almanah, is used in that case as well. So now
the גמרא says, like Michael said, that's one thing to explain a
rabbinic term maybe, but אלמנה דכתיב באורייתא מאי איכא למימר? Almanah dichtiv
be'Oraita mai ika lemeimar? How about the fact that it's a biblical
term? It says אלמנה, Almanah right? So it says אלמנה Almanah, all
the time in the תורה. Torah. And there was no idea of
a hundred זוז zuz. even if כתובה is, you base it on
the two hundred זוז for a בתולה for a virgin in the
תורה Torah for the מוהר הבתולות, mohar habetulot, the תורה Torah never
has any amount assigned for an אלמנה, Almanah so this whole thing
is a pure, for widows, the whole thing is a pure rabbinic
institution. How could you say the biblical term is based on that?
So the גמרא says, דעתידין רבנן דמתקני לה מנה. De'atidin rabanan dematkeni
lah maneh. Yeah, the תורה Torah called her an אלמנה Almanah because
the תורה Torah knew that eventually a thousand years later the rabbis
would create an institution that she gets a hundred זוז. And therefore
the תורה Torah had already called her an אלמנה anticipating a rabbinic
institution. So the גמרא says, ומי כתב קרא לעתיד? Umi katav kra
le'atid? Is the verse going to be written for some future institution
that's not going to happen for a thousand years? אין, yes. דכתיב
ושם הנהר השלישי חדקל הוא ההולך קדמת אשור. Dichtiv veshem hanahar hashlishi
Chidekel hu haholech kidmat Ashur. So the third river is חדקל Chidekel
which goes to the east of אשור. Ashur. ותני רב יוסף, Vetani
Rav Yosef, אשור זו סליקא. Ashur zu Selika. אשור Ashur is סליקא.
Selika. So big deal. So רש"י Rashi says, well, because that wasn't
around in the time of גן עדן. Gan Eden. So therefore the
תורה Torah was written on the future. So Joseph says, but it
was also around at the time of the תורה, Torah, right? So
it says, but it was around at the time of the משה.
Moshe. So when משה Moshe was writing it, it was still there.
Right, so yeah, it's really hard to know what the גמרא's answer
is. Okay. ומי הוה? Umi havah? And אשור Ashur didn't, and that
city of סליקא Selika didn't exist at the time of גן עדן.
Gan Eden. אלא דעתידה, Ela de'atidah, a place that will eventually be
called אשור. Ashur. הכא נמי דעתידה, Hacha nami de'atidah, here too eventually.
All right, I don't know what to say about this, it's a
completely bizarre statement. All right, moving on. ואמר רב חנא בגדתאה, Ve'amar
Rav Chana Bagdata'ah, so since we're דורש-ing doresh words, we have another
דרשה drasha of רב חנא בגדתאה. Rav Chana Bagdata'ah. מטר, Matar, rain.
So we're just going to do an alliteration of the מ. mems.
Sometimes we do a מ-ט-ר mem-tet-resh where we do a דרשה drasha
on each letter. Here it's just an alliterative of the מ. mem.
What does rain do? משקה, Mashkeh, waters the ground. מרווה, Meraveh, it
sates the ground. ומזבל, Umezabel, it fertilizes the ground. ומעדן, Ume'aden, and
sort of makes it moist. וממשיך, Umamshich, and causes and draws out
the fruit from the trees. אמר רבא בר ישמעאל ואיתימא רב יימר
בר שלמיא, Amar Rava bar Yishmael ve'iteima Rav Yeimar bar Shelamya, מאי
קרא, Mai kra, what do you see in the verse? תלמיה רוה,
Telameha raveh, its furrows you will sate. נחת גדודיה ברביבים, Nachat gedudeha
birvivim, you brought down unto its banks with like with rain, with
drops. תמוגגנה ברביב, Temogegena birviv, I'm sorry, נחת גדודיה ברביבים תמוגגנה, Nachat
gedudeha birvivim temogegena, with its drops of rain you will sort of,
you know, make it fertile. צמחה תברך, Tzimchah tevarech, you will bless
its sproutings, its fruit. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, מזבח,
Mizbe'ach, what is the word מזבח? Mizbe'ach? And again, an alliteration with
the מ. mems. מזיח, Mazi'ach, it sort of pushes away. ומזין, Umazin,
sort of feeds, I don't know what, you know, זן zan I
guess because it's לחם אלוהיך lechem elohecha although I don't know exactly,
you know, whatever, that's quite anthropomorphic. Anyway, מחבב, Mechabev, makes us dear.
ומכפר, Umechaper, and it atones. So the גמרא says, היינו מכפר היינו
מזיח, Hainu mechaper hainu mazi'ach, to atone is the same as to
be מזיח mazi'ach which means to sort of cast off our sins.
גמרא says no, מזיח mazi'ach doesn't mean to cast off our sins,
it means מזיח גזרות, mazi'ach gezeirot, it casts off evil decrees. ומכפר
עוונות, Umechaper avonot, atones for the sins. ואמר רב חנא בגדתאה, Ve'amar
Rav Chana Bagdata'ah, let's just do one more. תמרי, Tamrei, dates are
משחנן. Meshachnan. Warm up the body, משבען mesavan sate the body, משלשלן
meshalshelan cause for good, what's the word? Bowel movement, yeah, what do
you call those things that help the bowel movement? Laxatives. Okay, מאשרן
me'ashran and makes you happy, ולא מפנטן velo mefantan but don't make
you too like, I don't know what how to say מפנטן, mefantan,
spoiled or whatever, like overly what word do they use for מפנטן?
mefantan? Whatever. Finicky. All right, anyway. אמר רב, so says Rav, אכול
תמרי אל יורה, echol tamrei al yoreh, dates sort of make you
a little drunk was the assumption, I don't know how, so therefore
you shouldn't פסקן pasken after you eat some dates. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll
ask on that, תמרי שחרית וערבית יפות, tamrei shacharit ve'arvit yafot, if
dates in the morning and in the evening are good, if you
have them like around the meal time. במנחה רעות, Bemincha ra'ot, at
Mincha time they're not good, don't eat them on an empty stomach.
בצהריים, Betzohorayim, in the afternoon with your basically midday meal, your big
meal, אין כמותם, ein kemotam, there's nothing as good as them. Okay,
ומבטלו שלשה דברים umevatlo shelosha devarim and it puts away, it sort
of annuls three things: מחשבה רעה, machshava ra'ah, evil thought, it does
away with them, וחולי מעיים, vecholi me'ayim, bad, you know, stomach pains
because it's a, because it's a laxative, ותחתוניות vetachtoniyot and like a
hemorrhoid. Okay, so anyway, so how could you say you shouldn't פסקן?
pasken? Look how amazing dates are. So the גמרא says no, מי
אמרינן דלא מעלו? mi amrinan d'lo ma'alu? We didn't say they weren't
good. עילויי מעלו, ilu'ei ma'alu, they're great. ולפי שעתא טרדא ulefi sha'ata
tarda but but at when you eat them, they sort of, you
know, distract your thoughts. Maybe they don't make you drunk, but whatever,
they cloud your thinking a little bit. So they're great for the
body, they just cloud your thinking. So don't go ahead and what
do you call it, and פסקן pasken when you have had dates.
מידי דהוה אחמרא midei dahavei achamra like wine. Wine is great for
you, it's just don't פסקן pasken after you've drunk so after you've
drunk a little wine. דאמר מר השותה רביעית יין אל יורה De'amar
Mar hashotel revi'it yayin al yoreh even just a little, three fluid
ounces of wine, don't פסקן. pasken. ואיבעית אימא לא קשיא Ve'iba'it eima
lo kashya and if you want I could tell you it's not
difficult. הא מקמי נהמא הא בתר נהמא ha mikamei nahama ha batar
nahama depends before or after bread. Okay, דאמר אביי אמרה לי אם
de'amar Abaye amrah li em my mother, which means my nursemaid said
to me, תמרי מקמי נהמא כי נרגא לדיקולא tamrei mikamei nahama ke'narga
ledikula that if you have dates before you've eaten on an empty
stomach, it's like a hatchet to a palm tree. It's very destructive.
בתר נהמא Batar nahama after the bread, כי אברא לדשא ke'avra ledasha
it's like a bolt on the door. It's very healthy. So just
to end this up, דשא dasha a door, אמר רבא דרך שם,
amar Rava derech sham, that's that's the path in, I don't know.
דרגא Darga a step, אמר רבא דרך גג amar Rava derech gag
that's the way to the roof. So דרגא, darga, now we're sort
of doing a play on the two halves of the word. פורייא
Puraiya a bed, אמר רב פפא שפרין ורבין עליה amar Rav Papa
sheparin veravin aleha that's where you procreate. פורייא פרין ורבין. Puraiya parin
veravin. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak אף
אנן נמי נימא af anan nami neima we'll say similarly, אילונית ilonit
which is a woman whose body has not sort of physically matured,
so דכרניתא דלא ילדה. duchranita delo yalada. So אילונית ilonit is sort
of like a דכרניתא duchranita like a male ram like who cannot
have who cannot have children. So now we're done with our דרשות
drashot on various words. Okay.